Renzo Massobrio

Curriculum Vitæ

Office 4.14 Stevinweg 1 2628 CN Delft, the Netherlands **☎** (+31) 6 380 938 85 $\bowtie R.M.Massobrio@tudelft.nl$ www.fing.edu.uy/~renzom

My research centers on using data analysis and artificial intelligence to tackle complex urban problems. To achieve this, I combine methods from operations research, machine learning, network science, high-performance computing and geographic information systems. I specialize in urban mobility, with a focus on service operations and control, topological assessment of public transport networks, accessibility and equity, and passenger demand analysis.

Education

May 2021 Ph.D. in Computer Science, Universidad de Cádiz, Spain.

Advisors: Prof. Bernabé Dorronsoro and Prof. Sergio Nesmachnow

Thesis: "Learning for Optimization with Virtual Savant"

Dec 2018 M.Sc. in Computer Science, Universidad de la República, Uruguay.

Advisor: Prof. Sergio Nesmachnow

Thesis: "Urban mobility data analysis in Montevideo, Uruguay"

Sep 2015 Engineer in Computer Science, Universidad de la República, Uruguay.

Advisor: Prof. Sergio Nesmachnow

Project: "Taxi sharing optimization using evolutionary algorithms"

Academic appointments

Jan 2022 Postdoctoral researcher, Smart Public Transport Lab, Transport & Planning Depart-

-present ment, Delft University of Technology, the Netherlands.

Manager: Prof. Oded Cats

Topic: Network analysis for the comparative assessment of public transport networks in terms of

accessibility, equity, and recoverability in the event of failures

Jun 2016 Teaching and Research Assistant, Department of Transportation, Faculty of Engi-

-present neering, Universidad de la República, Uruguay.

Sep 2021 Researcher, Basic Sciences Development Program (PEDECIBA), Uruguay.

-present Research area: computer science

Jun 2019 **Researcher**, National System of Researchers, Uruguay.

-present Research area: Engineering and Technology

Dec 2014 **Teaching and Research Assistant**, Computer Science Institute, Faculty of Engineering,

-Jun 2016 Universidad de la República, Uruguay.

Awards and Honors

Updated: 2023-10-20

- 2022 Ph.D. thesis award, Universidad de Cádiz, Spain.
- 2021 **Ph.D. thesis award**, *Ph.D. thesis contest*, National Academy of Engineering, Uruguay.
- 2021 Best paper award, Travel time estimation in public transportation using bus location data, IV Ibero-american Congress of Smart Cities, Cancún, México.
- 2021 Masters thesis award, Master thesis contest, PEDECIBA-Informática, Uruguay.
- 2019 **Promising Young Researcher Award**, Ministry of Education and Culture, Uruguay.

- 2019 **Best masters thesis award**, XXVI Latin American Contest of Master Thesis, Latin American Center for Computational Studies (CLEI).
- 2015 **Best undergraduate thesis award**, Faculty of Engineering, Universidad de la República, Uruguay.

Grants

- 2022–2024 **Postdoc grant**, Margarita Salas fund for young doctors, European Union–NextGenerationEU.
- 2016–2021 Ph.D. grant, Fundación Carolina, Spain.
- 2016–2019 Ph.D. grant, National Agency of Research and Innovation, Uruguay.

Research Experience

Principal Investigator in Research Projects

- 2022–2023 Walking accessibility to the public transport network of Montevideo.

 Grants: "Ing. Oscar Maggiolo" Montevideo City Government Universidad de la República (~15 000€)
- 2020–2022 Territorial, universal, and sustainable accesibility: characterizing the intermodal transportation system in Montevideo.

 Grants: National Agency of Research and Innovation, Uruguay (~50 000€)
- 2019–2020 Study of mobility by public transport in the metropolitan area of Maldonado and accesibility to public services.

Grants: Office of Planning and Budget, Uruguay (~10000€)

Research stays

- Sep 2019 Centro Nacional de Alta Tecnología (CeNAT). Urban mobility data analysis in Costa Rica
- Dec 2018- Institut national de recherche en informatique et en automatique (Inria).
- Mar 2019 Optimization and machine learning for the permutation flowshop problem
- Jul 2016 Computer Science Department, CICESE Research Center.
 Transport planning in smart cities
- Feb Mar School of Computer Science & Informatics, Cardiff University.
 - 2016 Optimization of urban transit and related smart city problems using computational intelligence
 - Oct 2015 Superior Technical School of Informatics, Universidad de Málaga. Infrastructure location for vehicular networks
- Sep Oct Superior School of Engineering, Universidad de Cádiz.
 - 2015 SAVANT: Automatic Generation of Parallel Approximation Algorithms for Low-power Architectures Based on Machine Learning

Publications

*Complete list of publications available at www.fing.edu.uy/~renzom.

*In conference publications, the presenting author is <u>underlined</u>.

Refereed journal articles

S. Nesmachnow, R. Massobrio, S. Guridi, S. Olmedo, and A. Tchernykh. Big data analysis for travel time characterization in public transportation systems. *Sustainability*, 15(19), 2023.

- R. Massobrio, S. Nesmachnow, J. Muraña, and B. Dorronsoro. Learning to optimize timetables for efficient transfers in public transportation systems. *Applied Soft Computing*, 119:108616, 2022.
- R. Massobrio, S. Nesmachnow, F. Palomo-Lozano, and B. Dorronsoro. Virtual savant as a generic learning approach applied to the basic independent next release problem. *Applied Soft Computing*, 108:107374, 2021.
- R. Massobrio and S. Nesmachnow. Urban Mobility Data Analysis for Public Transportation Systems: A Case Study in Montevideo, Uruguay. *Applied Sciences*, 10(16):5400, 2020.
- D. Hernandez, M. Hansz, and R. Massobrio. Job accessibility through public transport and unemployment in Latin America: The case of Montevideo (Uruguay). *Journal of Transport Geography*, 85:102742, 2020.
- D. Peña, A. Tchernykh, S. Nesmachnow, R. Massobrio, A. Feoktistov, I. Bychkov, G. Radchenko, A. Y. Drozdov, and S. N. Garichev. Operating cost and quality of service optimization for multi-vehicle-type timetabling for urban bus systems. *Journal of Parallel and Distributed Computing*, 133:272–285, 2019.
- S. Nesmachnow, R. Massobrio, E. Arreche, C. Mumford, A. C. Olivera, P. J. Vidal, and A. Tchernykh. Traffic light synchronization for Bus Rapid Transit using a parallel evolutionary algorithm. *International Journal of Transportation Science and Technology*, 8(1):53–67, 2019.
- J. C. de la Torre, R. Massobrio, P. Ruiz, S. Nesmachnow, and B. Dorronsoro. Parallel virtual savant for the heterogeneous computing scheduling problem. *Journal of Computational Science*, 39:101048, 2019.
- R. Massobrio, S. Nesmachnow, A. Tchernykh, A. Avetisyan, and G. Radchenko. Towards a cloud computing paradigm for big data analysis in smart cities. *Programming and Computer Software*, 44(3):181–189, 2018.
- S. Nesmachnow, S. Baña, and R. Massobrio. A distributed platform for big data analysis in smart cities: combining Intelligent Transportation Systems and socioeconomic data for Montevideo, Uruguay. *EAI Endorsed Transactions on Smart Cities*, 2(5):1–18, 2017.
- R. Massobrio, S. Nesmachnow, J. Toutouh, and E. Alba. Infrastructure deployment in vehicular communication networks using a parallel multiobjective evolutionary algorithm. *International Journal of Intelligent Systems*, 32(8):801–829, 2017.
- R. Massobrio, G. Fagúndez, and S. Nesmachnow. Multiobjective evolutionary algorithms for the taxi sharing problem. *International Journal of Metaheuristics*, 5(1):67–90, 2016.

Book chapters

- D. Peña, R. Massobrio, B. Dorronsoro, S. Nesmachnow, and P. Ruiz. Designing a Sustainable Bus Transport System with High QoS Using Computational Intelligence. In Reference Module in Earth Systems and Environmental Sciences. Elsevier, 2022.
- R. Massobrio, S. Nesmachnow, and J. Toutouh. Multiobjective evolutionary algorithms for smart placement of roadside units in vehicular networks. In N. Nedjah, L. D. M. Mourelle, and H. S. Lopes, editors, *Evolutionary Multi-Objective System Design: Theory and Applications*, pages 1–36. Chapman & Hall/CRC Computer and Information Science Series, 2017.

Selected conference contributions

<u>Renzo Massobrio</u> and O. Cats. A typology of metro network system characteristics and topology. In 25^{th} Euro Working Group Transportation (EWGT), pages 1–3, 2023.

<u>Renzo Massobrio</u> and O. Cats. Topological analysis of public transport networks' recoverability. In 15th Conference on Advanced Systems in Public Transport (CASPT), pages 1–5, 2022.

<u>Renzo Massobrio</u>, S. Nesmachnow, and B. Dorronsoro. Virtual Savant: learning for optimization. In 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2020). Learning Meets Combinatorial Algorithms (LMCA) workshop., pages 1–5, 2020.

Renzo Massobrio. Urban mobility data analysis in Montevideo, Uruguay. In XLV Latin American Computing Conference, pages 1–18, 2019.

Renzo Massobrio, S. Nesmachnow, and B. Dorronsoro. Support Vector Machine Acceleration for Intel Xeon Phi Manycore Processors. In E. Mocskos and S. Nesmachnow, editors, *High Performance Computing*, pages 277–290, Cham, 2018. Springer International Publishing.

Teaching experience

Graduate and Postgraduate Courses

- 2017-present Foundations of urban informatics: data analysis and processing, Postgraduate course, Universidad de la República, (Module leader).
 - 2023–2023 **Public Transport Demand and Network Planning and Operations**, *Masters module*, TU Delft, (Teaching Assistant).
 - 2015–2020 **Evolutionary algorithms**, *Graduate and postgraduate course*, Universidad de la República, (Module co-leader).
 - 2016 **Distributed and Cloud Computing**, *M.Sc. module*, School of Computer Science and Informatics, Cardiff University, (Teaching Assistant).

Masters Thesis Supervision

- 2022—present Walking accessibility to the public transport network in Montevideo, Masters in Operational Research, Universidad de la República, Student: Sara Perera.
 - 2022–2023 Roadmap towards an unified European high-speed rail network, M.Sc. in Transport, Infrastructure and Logistics, TU Delft, Student: Filippo Borgogno.
 - 2022–2023 Quantification and Comparison of Hierarchy in Unimodal Public Transport Networks, M.Sc. in Transport, Infrastructure and Logistics, TU Delft, Student: Ketong Huang.
 - 2022–2022 **Topological Comparative Assessment of Metro Networks**, M.Sc. in Transport, Infrastructure and Logistics, TU Delft, Student: Sam Vijlbrief.

Bachelors Final Project Supervision

- 2021-present **Evolutionary algorithms and neural networks for sewer network design in Latinamerica**, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Students: Nicolás Herrera and Lucas Barbachan Rodríguez.
- 2018-present **Public transport optimization in smart cities**, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Student: Andrés García.

- 2022–2023 Passenger flow control strategy optimization in an urban rail transit network under epidemic conditions, *Joint BSc in Traffic and Transportation*, Beijing Jiaotong University and TU Delft, Student: Yike Hu.
- 2017–2018 Machine learning for automatic program generation, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Students: Mauro Picó and Marccio Silva.
- 2016–2018 **Big data processing for urban mobility**, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Student: Jonathan Denis.
- 2016–2018 Computational intelligence applied to urban transport optimization problems, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Student: Enzo Fabbiani.

Service to Profession

Management Activities

2022—present Young Member Coordinator, Standing Committee on Transit Data, Transportation Research Board.

Memberships/Affiliations

- 2023-present Latin American Chapter of the International Network for Transport and Accessibility in Low Income Communities (INTALInC-LAC).
 - 2018–2021 Thematic Network: "Totally integral, efficient, and sustainable smart cities (CITIES)".
 - 2017–2021 Iberoamerican Network for High Performance Computing.

Editor in journals

2023 Cities, Elsevier, Guest editor.

Journal Manuscript Reviews

PLOS One, Public Library of Science.

Travel Behaviour and Society, Elsevier.

Sustainable Cities and Society, Elsevier.

Journal of Public Transportation, Elsevier.

Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and Its Applications, Elsevier.

Journal of Rail Transport Planning and Management, Elsevier.

European Journal of Transport and Infrastructure Research, TU Delft.

Annals of Operations Research, Springer.

Applied Soft Computing, Elsevier.

International Journal of Metaheuristics, Inderscience Publishers.

Abstract and Applied Analysis, Hindawi.

Swarm and Evolutionary Computation, Elsevier.

Event Organization

Updated: 2023-10-20

- 2019-2022 **Public Transport and mobility seminar**, Faculty of Engineering, Universidad de la República, Montevideo, Uruguay.
 - 2015 International workshop: transport planning and smart cities, Faculty of Engineering, Universidad de la República, Montevideo, Uruguay.

Session Organization/Chair in Conferences

2023 Special session: Computational intelligence for smart cities, International Conference in Optimization and Learning, Málaga, Spain.

- 2021–2022 Special session: Urban Informatics, Big Data, Data Management, Analytics and Artificial Intelligence for Smart Cities, Ibero-American Congress on Smart Cities.
 - 2022 Special session: Optimization in public transport (Mobility and Traffic stream),
 International Conference on Operations Research (OR 2022), Karlsruhe, Germany.

 Technical Program Committee Member in Conferences
- 2018–2023 1st-6th Ibero-American Congress on Smart Cities.
 - 2023 16th International Conference on Computational Intelligence in Security for Information Systems, Salamanca, Spain.
- 2021–2023 International Conference in Optimization and Learning.
 - 2020 8th International Conference on Metaheuristics and Nature Inspired Computing, Marrakech, Morocco.
- 2019–2020 International Workshop on the Synergy of Parallel Computing, Optimization and Simulation.
 - 2020 **2**nd International Workshop on Parallel Optimization using/for Multi- and Many-core High Performance Computing, Barcelona, Spain.
 - 2019 International Conference in Optimization and Learning, Cádiz, Spain.
- 2017–2018 High Performance Computing Latin America.

Reviews for conferences

- 2023 11th Symposium of the European Association for Research in Transportation (hEART), Zurich, Switzerland.
- 2023 LV Simpósio Brasileiro de Pesquisa Operacional, São José dos Campos, Brazil.
- 2022 15th International Conference on Advanced Systems in Public Transport (CASPT), Tel Aviv, Israel.
- 2018 The 21^{st} IEEE International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems, Maui, Hawaii, USA.

Department/University Service

Masters thesis assessments

- 2023 Roadmap towards an unified European high-speed rail network, M.Sc. in Transport, Infrastructure and Logistics, TU Delft, Student: Filippo Borgogno.
- 2022 Quantification and Comparison of Hierarchy in Unimodal Public Transport Networks, M.Sc. in Transport, Infrastructure and Logistics, TU Delft, Student: Ketong Huang.
- 2022 **Topological Comparative Assessment of Metro Networks**, M.Sc. in Transport, Infrastructure and Logistics, TU Delft, Student: Sam Vijlbrief.

Bachelors final project assessments

- 2023 Process mining for urban mobility analysis, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Students: Bruno Rodao, Nicolás Carignani, Santiago Ferreira.
- 2021 Computational intelligence and learning for the prediction of traffic incidents, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Students: Guillermo Gabrielli, Ignacio Ferreira, Pablo Dalchiele.

- 2020 Computational intelligence for traffic data analysis and estimators learning, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Students: Juan Serra and Hernán Winter.
- 2020 Feeder bus line generation for public transport systems, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Students: Matías Dornel and Nicolás Erlichman.
- 2017 Neuroevolution applied to the automatic generation of artificial intelligence for videogame verification, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Students: Facundo Parodi and Sebastián Rodríguez.
- 2016 Solving the clustering problem using evolutionary algorithms, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Students: Lucía Carozzi and María Eugenia Curi.
- 2016 Scheduling in heterogeneous systems using hwloc, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Student: Diego Regueira.
- Cloud computing over open source infrastructures and the application to embryonic development study, Computer Science Engineering, Universidad de la República, Students: J. Martín, M. Escobar, G. Urrutia, S. Falero.

Participation in hiring committees

- 2022 Open Call for Teaching and Research Assistant position, Structures and Transport Institute, Universidad de la República.
- 2020–2022 Three Open Calls for Teaching and Research Assistant positions, Computer Science Institute, Universidad de la República.

Management activities

2021-present **Representative**, Academic subcomission for civil engineering postgraduate affairs, Faculty of Engineering, Universidad de la República.

Other professional activities

Consultancies

- 2022—present Associate consultant in Artificial Intelligence, Inter-American Development Bank. Evolutionary methods and artificial intelligence for the analysis and massive processing of data for water and sanitation systems
 - 2020–2021 Associate consultant in mobility, Opción Consultores.

 Origin-destination matrix generation within the project "Promotion of Electric Urban Mobility in Uruguay" funded by Deutsche Gesellschaft für Internationale Zusammenarbeit (GIZ) GmbH

Further education

Short Courses

- 2022 Coaching Individual Students and Project groups, TU Delft, Delft, Netherlands.
- 2022 Assessing Students and Master Thesis Projects, TU Delft, Delft, Netherlands.
- 2019 Planning Public Transport Services (PPTS), TU Delft, Amsterdam, Netherlands.
- 2017 **High-performance computing school (ECAR–HPC School)**, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, Argentina.
- 2017 **Summer School on Machine Learning**, Institute of New Imaging Technologies (INIT) Universitat Jaume I and Spanish Association of Pattern Recognition and Image Analysis (AERFAI), Benicássim, Spain.
- 2016 Geospatial data analysis using QGIS-Quantum GIS, REDES center, Buenos Aires, Argentina.

- 2015 Research connect: communication skills for researchers, British Council, Montevideo, Uruguay.
- 2014 **High-performance computing school (ECAR–HPC School)**, Universidad Técnica Federico Santa María, Valparaiso, Chile.

Languages

Spanish Native

English C2, Certificate of Proficiency in English, University of Cambridge

2009

Dutch A1, TU Delft

2022

References

Prof. Oded Cats

Department of Transport & Planning Delft University of Technology Building 23, Stevinweg 1 2628 CN Delft, Netherlands

⋈ o.cats@tudelft.nl

 \Rightarrow +31 (15) 27 81384

Prof. Sergio Nesmachnow

Computer Science Institute
Faculty of Engineering
Universidad de la República
Av. Julio Herrera y Reissig, 565
11300, Montevideo, Uruguay

⋈ sergion@fing.edu.uy

☎ (+598) 2714 2714 (ext. 12052)

Prof. Bernabé Dorronsoro

Computer Science Department School of Engineering Universidad de Cádiz Av. Universidad de Cádiz, 10 11519, Puerto Real, Spain ⊠ bernabe.dorronsoro@uca.es

a (+34) 956 483 354